A Guide to the Berkeley Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library,
Berkeley Family Papers 1536-present
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-113
circa 20,000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was placed on deposit by various members of the Berkeley family between 1933 and 1999. The papers were made a gift to the Library by Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and Edmund Berkeley, III on November 20, 2018.
Scope and Content
This collection primarily includes personal correspondence and legal and business papers of the Berkeley Family. Interfiled with these papers are extensive papers of the closely-related Noland family. The joined collection comprises about 20,000 items (ca. 85 Hollinger documents boxes on about 38 feet of shelving) dating between 1653 and 1930, with the heaviest concentration in the nineteenth century.
The Berkeleys were in Virginia very early, and settled first in Gloucester County. The family was in Middlesex County by the first decade of the eighteenth century where they built " Barn Elms" on the Piankatank River (on the north bank from present Berkeley Island). About 1820 they left Middlesex for " Aldie, " Loudoun County where they remained until 1882 when they moved to Red Hill, Albemarle County. The name "Edmund" appears in every generation.
The bulk of the Berkeley Papers concern business matters, especially farming operations on lands in Gloucester, Middlesex,King William, Prince William, Hanover, Lancaster, Loudoun, Albemarle, Clarke, and other counties.
Because of the close ties between the Berkeley and Noland families there are many common correspondents and much complementary material in the various groups of Noland and Berkeley families papers received by the Library from a number of donors over almost fifty years. Accordingly, the groups of Noland family papers have been interfiled into the Berkeley Papers. Separate folders have been used, and the accession numbers assigned to each group as it was received by the Library appear on the folders.
Much of the Noland material concerns "Airwell," Hanover County, and William Noland, Carter B. Berkeley, and Nelson Berkeley. Other items and topics of interest in the combined collections include: letters from Berkeley family members attending the University of Virginia; letters written by during the Civil War, especially by the Berkeleys serving in the Eighth Virginia Infantry Regiment. Letters written by Edmund Berkeley (1824-1915) relate many anecdotes about prominent persons such as the Marquis de Lafayette, James Monroe, Catesby ap Roger Jones, Andrew Jackson, Abel Parker Upshur, Henry Clay, John C. Calhoun, Daniel Webster, Charles Dickens, Sam Houston, and Theodore Roosevelt. He also describes events such as the explosion of the cannon named the "Peacemaker" on board the U.S.S. Princeton in 1844. Edmund served as Lieutenant Colonel of the Eighth Virginia, and his letters and those of his brother Norborne Berkeley (1828-), colonel of the Regiment, describe the many actions in which the regiment was involved such as Bull Run, Seven Pines, and Gettyburg, as well as life in Union prison camps, especially Johnson's Island, after their capture at Gettyburg following Pickett's charge.
The portion of the collection accessioned as #8221 includes personal correspondence of Landon C. Berkeley, Anne Poe Harrison (Landon's wife), Cynthia Berkeley, Edmonia Berkeley, and Francis Lewis Berkeley (1859-1942). Topics mentioned in these letters include: the election of 1856; horse racing; speeches by Dwight Lyman Moody; Wellesley College; the Miller School of Albemarle, Albemarle County, Virginia; Oregon in the 1880's; While Sulphur Springs, Virginia; slave hiring; Mary Custis Lee, [Chiswell Dabney] "Chilly" Langhorne; and William Mahone. Correspondents in this section include John Thompson Brown, John Warwick Daniel, Andrew Jackson Montague, John Barbee Minor, Thomas Nelson Page, Thomas Walter Harrison, and Micajah Woods.
There are bound volumes in #8221 that include class notebooks used by Francis Lewis Berkeley at the University of Virginia, 1896-1899, while taking courses in geology and agricultural chemistry, and his diary for 1906-1910 (Boxes 78-80). Other bound volumes include: a school notebook kept by Cynthia Berkeley in 1887 (Box 78); a mill ledger kept by William Noland at Aldie, Loudoun County; accounts, 1854-1885, kept by William Noland Berkeley; a common stock register, 1915-1930, of G.E. Smith with E.L. Rothschild Co.; and a trigonometry notebook, 1912.
Financial and legal papers in #8221 consist of deeds, receipts cancelled checks, and similar material. There is a large body of financial and legal papers of John Crissey of New York, an in-law of the Berkeleys.
Container List
- Correspondence and Business Papers
  - 1536 January -1717 December (Box Box 1)
  - 1718 January -1757 October (Box Box 2)
  - 1757 November -1768 February (Box Box 3)
  - 1768 March -1775 July (Box Box 4)
  - 1775 August -1785 March (Box Box 5)
  - 1785 April -1787 December (Box Box 6)
  - 1788 January -1791 December (Box Box 7)
  - 1792 January -1794 December (Box Box 8)
  - 1795 January -1797 May (Box Box 9)
  - 1797 June -1799 May (Box Box 10)
  - 1799 June -1801 May (Box Box 11)
  - 1801 June -1802 March (Box Box 12)
  - 1802 April -1803 November (Box Box 13)
  - 1803 December -1805 January (Box Box 14)
  - 1805 February -1807 January (Box Box 15)
  - 1807 February -1810 August (Box Box 16)
  - 1810 September -1811 December (Box Box 17)
  - 1812 January -1813 October (Box Box 18)
  - 1813 November -1815 October (Box Box 19)
  - 1815 November -1816 July (Box Box 20)
  - 1816 August -1817 November (Box Box 21)
  - 1817 December -1818 November (Box Box 22)
  - 1818 December -1820 April (Box Box 23)
  - 1820 May -1821 November (Box Box 24)
  - 1821 December -1823 January (Box Box 25)
  - 1823 February -1824 February (Box Box 26)
  - 1824 March -1825 April (Box Box 27)
  - 1825 May -1826 December (Box Box 28)
  - 1827 January -1828 March (Box Box 29)
  - 1828 April -1829 December (Box Box 30)
  - 1830 January -1831 March (Box Box 31)
  - 1831 April -1833 April (Box Box 32)
  - 1833 May -1835 August (Box Box 33)
  - 1835 September -1837 June (Box Box 34)
  - 1837 July -1839 August (Box Box 35)
  - 1839 September -1841 January (Box Box 36)
  - 1841 February -1842 October (Box Box 37)
  - 1842 November -1843 December (Box Box 38)
  - 1844 January -1845 December (Box Box 39)
  - 1846 January -1847 October (Box Box 40)
  - 1847 November -1848 December (Box Box 41)
  - 1849 January -1850 March (Box Box 42)
  - 1850 April -1851 February (Box Box 43)
  - 1851 March -1842 December (Box Box 44)
  - 1853 January -1854 February (Box Box 45)
  - 1854 March -1855 January (Box Box 46)
  - 1855 February -1856 August (Box Box 47)
  - 1856 September -1857 December (Box Box 48)
  - 1858 January -1860 November (Box Box 49)
  - 1860 December -1861 December (Box Box 50)
  - 1862 January -1863 September (Box Box 51)
  - 1863 October -1865 September (Box Box 52)
  - 1865 October -1868 July (Box Box 53)
  - 1868 August -1873 March (Box Box 54)
  - 1873 April -1877 May (Box Box 55)
  - 1877 June -1878 December (Box Box 56)
  - 1879 January -1880 January (Box Box 57)
  - 1880 February -1881 July (Box Box 58)
  - 1881 August -1883 May (Box Box 59)
  - 1883 June -1886 January (Box Box 60)
  - 1886 February -1888 March (Box Box 61)
  - 1888 April -1889 November (Box Box 62)
  - 1889 December -1890 December (Box Box 63)
  - 1891 January -1897 December (Box Box 64)
  - 1898 January -1903 February (Box Box 65)
  - 1903 March -1907 April (Box Box 66)
  - 1907 May -1912 November (Box Box 67)
  - 1912 December -1919 February (Box Box 68)
  - 1919 March -1932 May (Box Box 69)
  - 1932 June -1943 April (Box Box 70)
  - 1943 May -1947 April (Box Box 71)
  - 1947 May -1983 (Box Box 72)
- Undated and Miscellaneous Papers
  - Undated and Miscellaneous Papers (Box Boxes 73-77)
- Bound Volumes
  - "Smith's Lives of the Berkeley's", 1803 (Box Box 78)
  - Ledger of William Noland, (#8221, Vol. 1), 1817 -1818 (Box Box 78)
  - Memoranda Book, (#8221, Vol. 2), 1838 -1850 (Box Box 78)
  - Ledger of William N. Berkeley, (#8221, Vol. 3), 1854 -1885 (Box Box 78)
  - Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley, (#8221, Vol. 6), ca. 1880 (Box Box 78)
  - School Notebook of Cynthia Berkeley (#8221, V. 7), ca. 1887 (Box Box 78)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V. 8), 1896 (Box Box 78)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V. 9), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V.10), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V.11), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V.12), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Mineralogy Notebook of F. L. Berkeley, (#8221, V. 13), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V.14), 1896 (Box Box 79)
  - Geology Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley (#8221, V.15), 1897 (Box Box 80)
  - Diary of Francis L. Berkeley, (#8221, Vol. 16), 1905 -1910 (Box Box 80)
  - Account Book of Mrs. G.D. Smith in Account with E.L. Rothschild & Co., Stockbrokers, (#8221, V. 17), 1915 -1930 (Box Box 80)
  - Trigonometry Notebook of M. Sutherland (#8221, V. 18), 1932 (Box Box 80)
  - General Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley, ca. 1896 (Box Box 80)
  - English Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley, ca. 1896 (Box Box 80)
  - U.S. History Notebook, ca. 1934 (Box Box 80)
  - Autograph Book of Francis L. Berkeley, (Spine is labeled:"Mathematics U.S. Naval Academy"), ca. 1897 (Box Box 80)
  - Chemistry Notebook of J.T.D. Bell, 1892 (Box Box 80)
  - Chemistry Notebook of William N. Berkeley, No date (Box Box 81)
  - U.S. History Notebook of Francis L. Berkeley, 1877 (Box Box 81)
  - UVa Class Notes of Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., ca. 1930 (Box Box 81)
  - Papers Left by Charles W. Coleman, concerning the families of Smith, Tucker, White, etc., 1927 (Box Box 81)
  - Scrap Book #2, 1926 -1951 (Box Box 82)
  - Autobiography of Major General Randolph Carter Berkeley, USMC, (#8221, Vol. 19), 1959 (Box Box 82)
  - The commissioning of United States Ship "Berkeley" (DDG-15), [photo album], 1962 (Box Box 82)
  - Yearbook of Field Artillery Replacement Center, 4th Training Regiment, Fort Bragg, 1941 (Box Box 82)
  - Britain's Homage to 28,000 American Dead, 1952 (Box Box 82)
  - UVa Dedication of War Memorial Plaques, 1960 June 11 (Box Box 82)
  - "An Occasional Bulletin," The Virginia Historical Society, 1962, April (Box Box 82)
  - "The Iron Worker", 1957, Spring (Box Box 82)
  - Ephemera [match case and dress shirt studs], No date (Box Box 82)
  - Confederate envelopes, ca. 1861 -1865 (Box Box 82)
  - 19th Century postage stamps (Box Box 82)
  - two leather wallets, No date (Box Box 82)
  - Berkeley Family Bible (Box Box 83)
  - "Early Covers", No date (Box Box 83)
- Oversize Items
  - Family Bible (Lacks covers and end pages) (Box OS Box 1)
  - Printed Book, The History of England, Vol. XVI (Box OS Box 2)
  - Printed Book, The History of England, (title excised) (Box OS Box 3)
  - Ledger / Account Book, ca. 1801-1818 (Box OS Box 4)
  - Ledger / Account Book, ca. 1729-1760 (Box OS Box 4)
  - Business Ledger, ca. 1801-1802 (Box OS Box 5)
  - Business Ledger, William N. Berkeley (#8221), ca. 1857-1868 (Box OS Box 5)
  - Diplomas and Certificates (rolled) (Box OS Box 5)
  - Genealogical Charts (rolled) (Box OS Box 5)
  - Genealogical Charts (Box OS Box 6)
  - Certificates (Box OS Box 6)
  - Engraving, "Berkeley Castle" (photostat) (Box OS Box 6)